the sheer number of unknowns. Like when
there are more questions than answers,
it's a paradigm shift. When there are
job roles being created when people
don't even know if there is a job of
this name, like a DevOps engineer or
something like that, it's a paradigm
shift. I like this I like this way of
thinking about it.
And then from those practices that you
see people doing, hey, there's a trend
towards the patterns, and then hopefully
from the patterns we can distill, if
you're in this situation, this is one,
two, three. And then ultimately, I'm
just going to feed it all the
requirements, technical, business
requirements. It's going to produce
stuff similar to the implementation to
intend. Maybe the delivery is already
automated. And all of the sudden it pops
up and says, I think this is really
important. Should we save this as
knowledge?
You're listening to the AI Native Dev,
brought to you by Tessel.
Hello and welcome to another episode of
the AI Native Dev. Now, we've got some
exciting news coming up because there
are a couple of things which Patrick,
myself, and and and some of the other
Tessel Tessels in the team who are
working on is something called the AI
Native Patterns and the AI Native
Landscape. And we're going to jump into
a couple of these terms and maps and and
really talk about what it means to have
a set of patterns in the AI Native
space, what it means to be able to
create a map of the ecosystem with AI
Native tools, why it's important, and
most importantly, put this in the
community so that we can actually share
this as well as get a ton of
contributions back because it's really
important that for this to stay relevant
and up-to-date, we get a
ton of contributions from the community.
Joining me for this episode, as
mentioned, Patrick De Bois, and not your
first time on this podcast, Patrick, not
even the second time. Welcome back.
It's my pleasure. It's so exciting, so
interesting to talk about. So, my
pleasure.
Excellent. So, what do we what do we
talk about AI native dev first, Patrick?
And what do we talk about a paradigm
shift in in our ecosystem? To what scale
are we talking about in terms of changes
to our workflow, changes to our tooling,
changes to our processes?
When do we start talking about a
paradigm shift?
Yes, it's a good question. Me personally
in my life, it was often when there was
a new technology. Early days, it could
have been internet, then the cloud, then
mobile, serverless,
you name it, right? And right now we're
at
AI as a technology disrupting what we
do.
And that's for the point, right? Is it
just something we can add on and it's
fine, like we don't even mention it.
It's like a a small thing, or is it
actually impacting the way we work or
you know,
things that we really have to
do differently to make it worthwhile.
And so that paradigm shift is not And
sometimes I call it like slap-on AI,
right? On the top and you're good and we
have an AI product.
But once you start thinking about like,
okay, this is the surface, what can we
do deeper?
And how do we actually have to rethink?
Like we can't take for granted the past
or how we did it in the past. And that's
where it becomes like a paradigm shift.
It is not easy because,
you know, if it's an emerging thing, we
often don't know
how is it going to affect us? And
usually it takes a bit of time for us to
understand. People are trying certain
things and they see
what is possible and they look for the
boundaries of this new thing. They
probably overuse it a little bit just to
understand what the limits are. But when
that's substantial enough for changes
and having an impact and having a
benefit, you know, that in that case you
can talk about a paradigm shift.
I like the idea of it being the sheer
number of unknowns. Like when there are
more questions than answers, it's a
paradigm shift. When there are job roles
being created, when people don't even
know if there is a job of this name,
like a DevOps engineer or something like
that, it's a paradigm shift. I like this
I like this way of thinking about it. Of
course, yeah you mentioned the number of
DevOps movement, the cloud native
movement. When we talk about this,
is it is it important? Is it almost like
annoying to have a label like this, like
AI native, or is it actually useful to
to be able to create that hashtag, that
label?
Over the past,
we learned that whatever label we put on
it is probably the wrong label because
initially we don't understand fully what
it's about. And then eventually we
understand and then the whole term has
taken root. This has happened before
with cloud and then we call it cloud
native because all of a sudden there was
a shift, right? As we mentioned. With
DevOps, it was initially about the devs
and the ops sitting together, working
together. And then ultimately it became
like every bottleneck, like DevSecOps,
HR, you name it, fin, they all became
part of that. So, in that way it's it's
not a useful thing and having it maybe
not clearly defined, which is Agile at
its manifesto, still had a million of
questions. ITIL had 15 books, still a
million questions. Whatever you do to
exactly define is hard. The way that I
expressed it that if you have a label
for good and for worse that people are
like
vaguely understanding or believing or
kind of where the sense of where we're
going, this is important to get the
stories out. If you're doing something
new, you're trying something, hey, if I
just look at that label, I and the
hashtag, I can see
what emerging stories out there. And
when you use a new hashtag compared to
the old one, you know where the new
stories are coming from. So, that's a
very interest- instrumental, especially
in this beginning emerging
uh feeling where, you know, we we don't
know where we are. Yeah. One of the
labels in the broader industry, even
though we have machine learning
engineers and AI uh specialists, the
term AI engineer took root in a way
that, "Hey, if you're talking about AI
engineer, this is a person that bridges
the data together with the applications
and they're using new technology and
they bring things together. So, this is
again one of the new labels and often it
is also
uh
when a paradigm shift impacts the
organizational aspect, there is also a
shift in roles and in this case, there's
also the bridging of silos again of
bringing two things together that had a
friction in the past or maybe didn't
need to work together and go from there.
So, that's I think the value of of a
label is that we can track where the new
things are coming from.
Yeah, and I think one of the things with
the labels as well is a lot of the time,
like DevOps was a great example of it
and cloud native to some extent as well,
whereby people actually overused it and
meant different things by it and that's
why I think that the the patterns is
actually a really strong way of helping
to demystify a little bit some of the
labels as well cuz I think while it's
good to have that label so we can refer
to this movement, refer to this change
in a paradigm shift, it's important to
actually be able to break that down and
state clearly what does that mean and
that's a lot of what we've worked in
these patterns today. Of course, you
mentioned as well there the people,
there's a big shift in what people are
needing to do, what people's roles are
going to need to be. That's obviously
something that is a little bit slower to
adapt to and and it's something that I
think is a little bit more emotive,
right, as well because when we think
about the unknowns, it's okay for
technologies to have unknown gaps and to
find their own way, but when it's when
it's us as people and humans who are
trying to understand our relevance in 5
to 10 years, it's a far more daunting
shift.
Yes, and the questions like, "Oh, will
AI replace my job?" And what will come
of that? Ironically, at the early days
of DevOps, everybody said, "Oh, go away
or I'll replace you with a shell script,
right?" That was the same automation
feeling, the feeling that you could be
redundant, new technology does part of
your job or or kind of does. Now, I
think if you look at it in the broad
sense, technology influences
the roles and the organization and how
we work together if if there's a
significant impact.
Also, the other way around. But But I
think, let's say we're here talking
about developers, developers do a
multitude of actions, right? They're not
just coding, they're talking to their
their product owner, they're looking at
things in production, they're trying to
solve a new problem. So, they have a
bunch of different tasks, right? And if
you look at it this way, is that if you
unbundle all the tasks of all the things
they're doing, some pieces with a new
technology get replaced, some things get
enhanced, some
things just vanishes because it's a
solved problem. And so, that's how you
look at this new trend of the technology
and what we focused on in in the kind of
how we
group things together is if you're a
dev,
what kind of things are changing about
the stuff that you do? And how do they
actually
allow you to do new things? Or what
should you be looking for? Like, when I
go to when there's something with my
car, I don't know anymore like how to
fix it, I go to a garage, right? So,
there's certain level of abstractions
that we solved in a certain way that I
don't have to understand. I still in
Belgium have to know how to drive. If
you take that away, there's something
else that could be replacing this. So,
this kind of unbundling is important uh
and seeing
if technology matures that well
in a way that it's not just a simple
thing that is added,
but it can completely take like
a task over that it's done autonomously,
then that's a completely different
impact. And uh a model that comes up
quite often in this kind of like uh
things is the the Tesla model of the
self-driving car. How far is it? Does it
need a little bit of help? Is it pretty
much okay, but there's an exception, or
can we do everything together? And
that's the beauty right now in the
technology is that the spectrum so big.
Some things we're only getting started.
Other things we're getting better at,
and so we're on that curve almost like a
maturity curve or kind of an evolution
of how how autonomous the technology can
help us. And the more autonomous it
gets, the more we are influenced.
And when we talk about that maturity
curve, I think one of the things that we
first need to be able to do really well,
particularly when we think about
maturity, which we're obviously at a
very early stage at here, is be able to
describe what good looks like or be able
to describe the space that we're in
because then we can understand, okay,
are we doing certain things? Are we
doing certain things poorly? Where do we
need to improve? And
we talked about the naming here quite a
bit, didn't we? When we talk about we're
originally thinking about AI native
developer or development principles,
then practices, and we landed on
patterns. Why is naming here important?
And secondly, why do we even need
patterns?
Yes.
So,
the way that
we defined it was
a pattern is something you observe that
is happening.
Right, so
and we'll we'll get into the details. A
principle is something that people
should do. So, it's it's much more
harder. Like, you should do A, B, and C.
It's It's almost like prescriptive,
right? We're We're not there yet at the
point because we're still observing, and
we are seeing what people experiment
with, and hopefully that distills it
ultimately into a set of principles like
we could do.
Now, how do we learn about this? If
people have a bunch of tools, and
they're trying to see what they can do,
and they they kick different areas, and
they they go a little bit wild,
they're doing a bunch of practices,
and they're trying stuff. And then from
those practices that you see people
doing, "Hey, there's a trend towards the
patterns."
And then hopefully from the patterns, we
can distill
"If you're in this situation, this is 1
2 3 you should do." That's where
initially we we had maybe the thinking
about this is principles. We can tell
you exactly
what we need to do. And this this turned
out maybe a little bit to be
over-optimistic
in the state that we're at because it's
still so emerging and and in in moving
so fast. This So, that gave it a little
bit of a nuance in in the meaning, and
we settled on on patterns right now.
Yeah, and it's fun actually when we talk
about I I love the phrasing of where how
we talk about it as observations because
because it's that fun stage where
actually we're nowhere near mature
enough whereby this is exactly what you
said, is something whereby we know
exactly what good looks like. We need to
know we need you to do these things in
this order to be able to get to where
you need to be. But what we're even
talking about here today, by the time
this even gets released and with further
community feedback, what we have today
might even change slightly, whether it's
slightly in the naming, whether it's
slightly in the actual activities and
things like that. And I think I know
this is the way you love to work,
Patrick, but it's you call it building
in the open, right? So, being able to
think in the open, think on social
networks, whereby you can get that
community feedback, you understand
whether what you're saying clicks with
people or whether they have cases that
actually fall outside of your
categorization or your or the labels
that you're making, and you adapt it to
that. And I think that's a really
important way, particularly with
AI-native development, which is very
broad, to make sure we're not just
focusing on a specific the classic
coding style, but actually it's much
broader than that. And I think one of
the things that we're talking about here
is this is a very this is like a V0.1
that we're going to be talking about.
And we'll cover them, but what one of
the things that we really want is for
the for for for people to have a look,
read it, consume it, and then actually
say, "Actually, I would love to propose
this." Or here's my feedback on this
pattern because these will change over
time. And we're like we say, we're not
at that stage where this is in stone.
Yeah, the patterns are on AI-native
dev.io. Right now, there's a few blogs
that are available, and they will
continue to come out. We would love that
that contribution, that feedback. Ping
us hello@ainativedev.io
or directly to yourself, Patrick, across
socials, etc. But yeah, we absolutely
want that feedback. So, let's go through
Anything you want to add on that,
Patrick, or ready to go through the
patterns?
No, please share. Like this is
like a community effort, and it's
important to grow. And if you don't
share the stories, yeah, how else are we
going to improve our craft?
Absolutely. So, why don't we go through
the first one then? From producer to
manager. Talk us through that.
Yes. So,
the canonical example of this is you're
a developer, you're writing code, all of
a sudden with the new tooling, you're
not writing the code.
It's being completed.
Maybe it already generated the whole
file. Maybe it generated a seven files.
So, the first
thing that people notice is that they'll
have to proof things.
So, they become the reviewer. Pull
requests, they say, "This is good. This
is bad. This is what I want." So,
instead of being the producer and
actually doing the stuff, you're having
that review. And that's important is
having to understand what good looks
like. Now, if you take that a step
further
towards production, i- imagine something
happens, right?
You'll have to manage and say,
"Do this. Do that." And you don't have
that situational awareness anymore. Like
much like a manager, you're the things
are helping you to understand this. And
uh this is a paradigm shift that
maybe a lot of people don't like because
they don't feel they they still want to
do the coding, but it's definitely a
pattern that's happening and pushing us
to go there.
And this isn't a 100, this is a There's
a sliding scale here, right, as well. If
you were to use something like Let's
grab a couple of tools. Let's say
Copilot, for example, and let's maybe
pick a Bolt or something like that, Bolt
or New or Lovable or something like
that. Copilot, obviously, you are still
You're much closer to that producer, but
you're still having something done in an
automated way, but obviously the lift is
smaller in terms of what it will
produce, and you are almost like a
micromanager of the lines of code.
Whereas, of course, if you're on the
Bolt or the Lovable or the the whatever
it is side on that far side, the V0,
you're expecting more to be automated
before you actually look at it. You're
giving much higher-level tasks, uh more
feature-related tasks than code-related
tasks, and expecting it to fill in that
gap. So,
at what stage are folks AI native here?
Is there a level or are we just on this
AI native scale where, you know, you
might be slightly more producer, you
might be slightly more manager, but you
you exist on this scale?
Yeah, so it the different tools will
allow you to do different kind of
practices. And uh so, that's the pattern
distills to it. Like the simple thing
is, yes, I accept or no. You're also a
manager in a way, but this is the like
the smallest thing. If you think like
broadly, I could have seven agents kick
off, come back to me in the morning, and
I'm going to say what good looks like,
right? And that could be something like
a Devin or something completely out
there that does cycles. Big spectrum on
different things, and then in production
as well, oh, things happens. Oh, the
bots are trying a few things versus
the bots tell me where kind of the
documentation is. There's a big
difference in the spectrum that you can
do. So, it doesn't inherit in the tools,
and we'll expect the tools to eventually
implement all of those features, but
different tools will be at the different
level of what you can do as a practice
in there as well to manage things.
Yeah, yeah.
And especially the cognitive load comes
in there as well as a manager. Like, you
have to understand the whole system. You
have to understand all the pieces. So,
that's another thing on how can we
reduce that as an aspect? Maybe our IDEs
will change on how we look at the code,
how it helps us understand the code, how
it deals with those issues, and then
ultimately
we'll have to do training because we're
not that good at coding anymore. So, you
see, it's like a big spectrum that we're
heading towards that direction. And it
is very similar to the DevOps thing,
like automation spectrum on how mature
you are. Definitely there.
Yeah, and the second pattern is similar
in it sounds similar, but there's
actually quite a fundamental difference
between one and two. The second pattern
is moving from implementation to intent.
Now, this sounds a little bit similar in
the sense of you produce implementation,
you manage your intent, but this is
really talking about the focus of how we
as developers are looking at what we're
actually producing. it. talk us through
that.
Yes.
So, the difference between both patterns
are the previous one we discussed was
more like operationally you're the one
who says, "Ah, this is good. This is
what I want." The second pattern, see I
wanted to say principle, the second
pattern
is about I express the intent that it
should do. So, I'm not like
after the fact. This is before it it
gets generated. And also there is a big
spectrum. You could say, I go into my
IDE, I press tab, right? Okay, got an
implementation. If I do a
prompt, I describe what I want it. If I
go into the chat and have that kind of
more iterative loop, what people are now
calling vibe programming or vibe coding,
but you get into I specify what I want.
If you take that all the way up to, hey,
I'm going to send you an image, please
code the front end like this.
My back end should have this directory
structure. So, you get more into
specifications. So, it's not anymore a
prompt, but again, it's a big spectrum.
And then ultimately, I'm just going to
feed it all the requirements, technical,
business requirements. It's going to
produce stuff, and then I am the manager
who has to say yes, no. So, this is how
both go hand in hand. Like the first one
is probably
the one that people notice the more, but
the second shift they're going through
is like all of a sudden I'm not coding
anymore, yes.
I express what I want through a certain
way, all the way up from a prompt to
here's a bunch of requirements and
figure this out.
Yeah. And at Tess, we call we refer to a
lot of this as that spec centricity
almost. So, that leaning into something
which is more natural language oriented
potentially, but something whereby it's
all intent. It's describing what
behavior we want a component or or or or
some piece of software to satisfy. And I
think this is a trickier one for us to
overcome, I feel, as humans because when
we move from a producer to a manager, a
lot of the time, if you think about the
the evolution of a software developer's
role as they effectively maybe they they
as they get more senior, they build a
team maybe and so forth, they are
thinking about things from a higher
level, but they're still thinking about
it in that architecture and code style.
From the implementation to intent, it's
very different cuz this is a massive
mind shift in terms of how we actually
provide that information. And if we are
shifting away from this kind of this
implementation, we're essentially trying
to
produce the right specifications or pro-
pro- provide the right requirements.
Almost like moving to the mentality of a
PM, right? Because that's that's
essentially what that role um needs to
deliver on.
The first um pattern was maybe become
more like an ops person because they
take in and they say yes, no, and when
an incident happened, they make
decisions. The second pattern is
definitely closer to the product owner
who says, "I understand my business.
This is how I should look like."
Or as an architect, like this is what I
want it to do and how technology look
should look like. So, there's definitely
an impact in there. And you you just see
in all the tools, they're developing
more and more kind of that
spec-centricity built into the IDE. So,
it isn't as clunky as put it in the
prompt and give it a markdown file. This
will become like a full citizen in the
IDE as just describe what you need. And
then we'll go in smaller steps
to being the implementation.
And it's quite interesting you mentioned
the IDE there cuz we've when we talk and
envision such change, I guess the big
question there is and you don't have to
answer this today, but it's definitely
something worth thinking about is is the
IDE even the appropriate place to do
these things because perhaps when we
talk about implementation to intent and
we're thinking about the written word
and and how we describe, you know,
pieces of functionality
is we lean into the product manager
perspective, but is a more a product
manager interface/tool
more appropriate for that? And we can go
into that in a bunch of depth, which uh
I don't think we should today, but it
it's interesting to think about when we
talk about AI AI native and not slapping
AI AI on, but actually building it in
from the ground up, we need to rethink
all of these things for it to be a
proper a proper paradigm shift, right?
When we think, what is the best way of
doing this from the ground up? Is are
these assumptions that I'm making about
my tool set still valid? Yeah,
interesting to see how that goes
forward.
Yeah, and definitely it depends on how
good the tools will become.
Right.
Right, because if
they only do halfway, then we can't have
the fully spec and we'll have to figure
out what the code is still doing.
Yeah.
But maybe there's other ways that is
being improved. Conflicting in
requirements is a fun one
because often a dev gets input to a
board or like a design or something, and
then they do their best to understand
what needs to be done. And they make an
interpretation of this,
Yeah. And collaboration is getting
history.
matches indeed. But often there's like
conflicting things on how fast you can
go to production and then performance uh
requirements, and then the business says
it needs to be cheap. And so, you see,
having that discussion will be actually
also part of a collaborative thing
Yeah.
where it's not just, "Oh, the technology
will solve it." It pushes actually to
have the conversation uh with kind of
the product managers, and for them with
the customers or the business.
Yeah, yeah.
Like good devs already do this, but it
is going to be amplified as they break
out into this realm as well.
Number three, pattern number three is
from delivery to discovery. What does
this mean, Patrick?
Yeah, and it doesn't mean we don't have
to do delivery.
Ah, damn.
For a moment.
Similar to the implementation to intend,
maybe the delivery is already automated,
right? We've done a lot of CICD
pipelines. So, that kind of is more and
more a solved problem.
Now,
what does a discovery mean? If it's so
cheap to generate things,
we might generate five different
versions of this. So, we're discovering
which of them is right. In the past, we
only had time for one
and we didn't know that. And if we can
generate multiple of them, then we can
also
have feedback from the customers, the
ones they like. So, you become more of a
a product discovery and even prototype
like faster several different options,
which one they like. Mhm. And and so,
you you have that discovery where in the
past you were like heads down in the
delivery of one option and that was
bogging us down. And I think that's
very strongly as
almost like building the right thing
instead of
building the thing right. Uh and that
comes again to the product owner and the
business uh and the experimentation, but
it could also manifest itself into the
technology. Hey, we have three tools.
Which is the best one? We have three
algorithms. Which one should we use? So,
also there's a discovery of technology
and options we could take in the
architecture which then lead to
specifying this into the intend which
then eventually leads to becoming the
manager of one it's implemented. There's
some thought in this that clicks all
everything together.
Yeah, no, absolutely. And it this
actually reminds me back to the session
that we had with Hana Fox. One of the
areas that she talked about was if when
you remove the bottleneck of effectively
the slow piece being the delivery, the
coding, and then actually taking that to
production,
you then realize that actually the
bottleneck is more on the PM. And from
that she meant when we can produce
everything we want to, the question then
is what's the right thing to produce?
What's the right thing to deliver? And
yeah, she envisioned a a future whereby
we make thin, small feature deliveries,
gather that feedback, and it's actually
that feedback cycle that needs to be as
fast as you can possibly get it so that
we can understand that feedback and then
iterate onto what our what our next
deliverable is. And that's really a lot
of what the discovery is here as well,
right? In terms of being able to
understand what is the right thing
before before um pushing the next piece
out.
In the past we had to do feature
flagging. Does a customer like A better
than B or something like that?
But imagine that the AI is having a
conversation with that user and actually
changes the code
as they're chatting with us, right? So
that that that's also like you can do
discovery in production. You can do your
discovery of ideas or in the technology.
Uh so it's definitely in a lot of the
areas, but hopefully the time that is
freed by not doing the other thing,
uh we can go more into that realm. And
there's definitely a bunch of tools that
are supporting this new discovery in a
good way and that assists that kind of
uh friction uh to to be overcome.
Yeah, there sounds like a meme there,
Patrick. I don't do discovery often, but
when I do it in production. I like I I
like that new meme. We'll we'll run with
that.
Number four, four out of four, from
content to knowledge. This sounds like a
very wise one, Patrick. Walk us through
this.
Yeah. It also also sounds like a little
boring one to me.
But I'll explain why I think it's it's
there. Imagine everything can be done by
someone like a machine.
And we're the managers of the machine
and yes, we have specified what we want
it to intend and we discovered a bunch
of things.
What you really want in an in a company
then to keep the competitive advantage
is to turn all the things that you
learned insights in every document and
or like all the things into knowledge
because that's ultimately
your discriminator against all the other
ones that you keep that knowledge inside
of your company.
Now, it could be we try this way in
business, our customers like this.
But you can also see this more
simplistic. As a developer, you have a
code base.
A couple of things. When a new developer
comes in,
there's a ramp up time of knowledge that
they have to learn that new code base.
When a developer leaves, there's a ton
of knowledge that in is in their head
that you have to capture. So also those
pieces if you can extract that and right
now a lot of it is almost like somewhere
in a wiki, gets out there, nobody cares.
So if we can nurture those contents to
keeping that on top of knowledge,
both the humans and the AI will benefit
from this because we know the much
cleaner your data is,
your content, your knowledge actually it
becomes better. For me, the one that
made it click as a category was in the
tool that I have
you have a conversation much like the Vi
programming and kind of what do you want
to you express the intent and you it
keeps asking you questions. Why do you
think like why would you do we do this
and how and all of the sudden it pops up
and says,
I think this is really important. Should
we save this as knowledge?
Mhm.
So it's inherently learning from us
because then the next time it suggests
something it's actually better and that
actually helps us as well because
a new person can come in
take the code base, the code base is
turning to lessons using AI
go nuts, learn. Here's all the context,
here's the historical information.
Again, this is maybe
closer to the dev but in a general sense
this is also something happening into
other parts of the organization and
dealing with the knowledge as the
ultimate form of kind of value in there.
And do you feel this is a this is one
that can go stale as well whereby with
data there is data that is correct at a
certain point and sometimes incorrect at
that same point as well if it's if it's
poorly put together. Is this an area
whereby we need to be very careful about
the truisms and what's correct, what's
not correct because we can really trip
over assumptions in this space. We need
to be careful with that quality of data.
Yes, but that but that's part of that
knowledge management is is keeping tabs
on the quality of the data. Is it our
data?
Yeah.
Like a terminology that we used to years
ago and now it means something else. So
there's definitely that as well like
a timely piece or historical piece.
The tools have changed so whatever we do
there is irrelevant and we'll have to
find it maybe in a Slack channel, we'll
have to find it in a meeting and this is
also a trend that you see in the
technology where you have to feed in a
lot more context, content to actually
distill this and keep this up to date.
Yeah.
And as it is more in that feedback loop
we'll get reminded that it is outdated
if we don't get the right answer. So
when the manager or the reviewer comes
up and okay, okay, why are you saying
this? Oh, let's update this. So so
that's amplifying that pattern as well.
Yeah. No, they all work together and
that's it's not something which has come
together by fluke is many hours of
thought thought from yourself and many
others. Yeah, just to reiterate I think
one thing that we'd love certainly is
feedback on this. How is this resonating
with yourselves? Is this Are you looking
at this in a similar way? Are there
areas that you feel are more important?
Are there parts here or there are there
patterns here that you feel shouldn't be
here, but should be replaced with
something else? We'd love to We'd love
to hear that. And of course, naming's
hard, Patrick. Let's make sure these
these are named correctly so that they
are as as clear as possible. But yeah,
we want that feedback. How would we like
that feedback, Patrick? What's the best
way of the community contributing?
Yeah, so we'll we'll be releasing a few
blog posts. Like one is the overview and
then we go with deeper into each of the
kind of patterns. And we'd love to have
you comment on the blog post and share
and like
that it's visible for everybody. It
doesn't only have to be visible for us.
We're doing this like you said in the
open and then we can learn from that.
So, definitely looking forward to that.
Yeah, I guess the Discord chat would be
a good place as well to have those have
those deeper discussions as well, which
are maybe a little bit more a little bit
more back and forth. So, make sure you
feel free to join the Discord chat and
and ping out on there so we can we can
talk there as well.
for a deeper chat or conversation
instead of us like
putting comments and ping-ponging there.
50 comment thread. Yeah, absolutely.
Now, let's We've talked a little bit
about the I don't want to say the
practices there, the patterns. We talked
a little bit about people and how roles
and tasks and things like that change.
We haven't touched on on tools just yet.
Now, one of the things that fingers
crossed we're releasing this week and
I'll I know we're recording this last
week. So, all being well, we're we have
released or very soon to release
an a landscape, an AI native dev tools
landscape. And the goal of this is
really to categorize the ecosystem to be
able to provide a map of where various
tools sit so that we can look at the
overall ecosystem a little bit more
holistically. And we need this, right,
Patrick? Because we we can't think about
this type of a paradigm shift without
tools. As much as they're driven by lots
of different groups, whether it's open
source, whether it's vendors, it's
something which we need to be able to
enforce our ways of thinking, to to
actually build those practices those
practices out.
In the DevOps world, a lot of people
said, "It's not about the tools, it's
about the people and the practices that
people do." But without the tools, you
can't do it. It is important that we
know which of the tools are out there,
and that's the catalog gives that clear
overview of what is out there. Because a
lot of people don't have the time to
look all the time at whatever niche
slack or channel to to see what's
released. So, we're opening up that like
view and that perspective for people of
the tooling that is out there.
And that's important. And then once we
have that catalog, we can
talk about the
patterns and the practices that you do
in those tools, and and then relate it
to that. So, well, that's why we're
losing both kind of the patterns and the
tool catalog, because they help us find
the supporting practices that people do.
Yeah, cuz it's like
initially to group all the tools into
the practices, but then we figured out a
practice is not always related to a
specific tool. It is broader. Like your
manager could be everywhere. Discovery
could be anywhere. And that's where we
maybe went back to what we currently
know as roles. Hey, you're doing
development or a task, right? Because
then you can see how that task is
changing with AI in there, and that's
how we decided to regroup if ultimately
of what people know right now, so they
can see what the new tooling brings
there, and then they can look at the
patterns to see which kind of new set of
practices that should be doing those
tools.
And it's interesting, because this is
again one that's changed a couple of
times behind the scenes before before it
was released. And I'm sure again it will
be changed in future as well for sure.
I'll be amazed if it if we got it right
in first time around. So it's definitely
one of those things where again,
everything from naming all the way
through to is this tool in the right
category or should this tool is there a
new tool that we almost certainly
haven't added that's all amazing
feedback that we want to add back in. So
community contributions are absolutely
paramount here. When we think about maps
and landscapes and ecosystem menus
almost essentially, how are these useful
for people? How should someone think
about taking value out of this? What are
the options?
When you look at a map,
I think the first thing that people do
is try to locate themselves on a map.
Yeah.
What are we doing? Like where are we?
And it's no different here. Okay, so if
you look at the different practices, are
we doing this or are we not doing this
or like where should be be going or be
expanding? So it gives you
where you are and then where to expand.
And the same thing is with the tooling.
Maybe right now you only know of, you
know, GitHub Copilot, which is a good
tool. You can build a lot of things
around that as well and use other tools
to complement that. So I noticed that
the first value that people get is
we didn't know that all existed. We It's
like open wide opening, eye-opening for
them to see it. Oh, it could do all
this. We didn't know.
Because if you don't know that it's
possible, you will not start thinking
about kind of the new patterns and not
do the practices. So that's how I I
think it opens up. Now,
keeping track of the space is definitely
also useful because it's not the map
will change.
And so that we change the categories or
maybe the wording or the patterns,
hopefully not too much. Wording will
change and that's okay in the in the
state we are.
And then after that, I hope somebody
says, "Hey, I found something that's new
and we we haven't gotten there." So,
there is a discovery of what most people
think and the things that are out there,
maybe the more fringe things is, "Yeah,
I never thought of this." So, we're
learning and innovating in the sense
that somebody else did something new.
And And that kind of expansion is
hopefully what gives us a more complete
map ultimately
for people to work with.
Yeah, and it's one of those challenges
where we talk about a a more complete
map. We'll never have a complete map.
And there will it's one of those things
where we we want to try and avoid stale
data, and we want to make sure that the
right tools are in the right place. So,
this is it's important that we do get
those contributions.
landscape.ai/nativedev.io
is the place to go to to to take a look
at that. You'll see the various
categories, as you mentioned,
categorized by how we think about
software development today in terms of
coding and testing and so forth. Yeah,
if there's anything there that you feel
is incorrect or you want to add, feel
free to to follow the instructions
landscape.ai/nativedev.io
to to contribute there. It's one of
those AI is one of those spaces where,
of course, there is such a vast number
of new startups and things like that
every day. The pace is insane. But also,
many tools do
a broad number of things as well. How do
you deal with such vendor sprawl in the
in the landscape, Patrick?
Yeah, so
our rule right now is to likely, let's
say we have 20 tools in a certain
category.
If that explodes, somewhere there must
be a differentiator. It can't be
otherwise, right? So, we'll split that
up eventually to a a broader kind of
area. Now, it's not always easy that we
found what is the differentiator. I'll
give the example of, okay,
today you're IDE, and then tomorrow you
are you have the ability to do specs. We
already talked about specs. Maybe
there's seven different
uh levels you can implement specs or
agents. And agents could be implemented
in seven different kind of variations.
So, you can't group it by agents because
every tool eventually will have agents.
Every tool will eventually have specs.
Now, we try to say a couple of rules.
And one is
it's more like a rule of thumb.
If you take away the AI from the
product, will it still work? That kind
of gives you an idea of is it AI native,
right? Um now, some tools will belong to
certain categories, and especially with
the the move towards a platform who
tries to do different things. And And
And you'll see kind of tools being
bought by one vendor to become that
broader spectrum, much like you saw in
the SDLC. And yes, then you'll maybe
have a primary category or secondary
category. Uh but right now, it seems to
be a little bit of the exception. And
we're trying to steer clear and keep
them in their own category. But yeah, it
it is challenging. I can tell you that.
If categories fails, we always have like
keywords and tags for people to to do uh
find what they need. I I I want open
source. We can't just say here's the
open source one and all. So, they can
find those just simply with a tag.
That's really interesting. To be able to
say that here are the categories, but
actually we're tagging as well. So, that
if you click on some of the tags, you'll
see those that are just the open source
and so forth.
Yes, indeed. Yeah.
We did think originally also about
having AI native dev categories. And we
mentioned this as as thinking about the
initial categories in and around SDLC.
Do you think that will change in future,
Patrick? Or do you feel like the SDLC
the the way of us thinking about
different stages in the SDLC will
continue beyond the major changes that
we see in AI native development.
There will be new more AI native dev
categories. Although the others are
already considered AI native dev, but
new categories be merging of things that
are so specific or that expand so hard
that they become their own ecosystem of
tools.
Mhm.
Uh and and that's likely to happen.
Let's say if you do more technical
experimentation, that's not built in the
existing tools, but that might become a
category of, you know, just try out
seven different coding languages with
seven different kind of runtimes and
it's probably now
expanding of what could happen that it's
actually could happen, but it's an it's
just an example of
something that could become its own
category in there. The same thing with
knowledge management is something that
could become its own category as well.
Yeah. Yeah, we look forward to see how
it it evolves. And of course, as I
mentioned before, community
contributions are are very important
here. So, feel free to to contribute to
both the patterns
and also to the landscape. So, Patrick,
this has been super exciting and of
course, do check out AI native dev.io,
the new site to to check out both of
those on the blog and landscape. AI
native dev.io for the landscape map as
well. Patrick, is
wow, we're already run out running out
of time. So, I just want to say thank
you very much for sharing a lot of your
work here. And I know this is just the
start because I know how much the the
community contributions and discussions
really do evolve the thought process
here and and churn all the thoughts and
evolve how the AI native dev landscape
should look.
Yeah, it's like an ever shifting puzzle,
but it's so interesting to try to solve
it.
Yeah. Yeah, absolutely. Thanks very
much, Patrick. And and yeah, thanks very
much for listening on the AI native dev.
Be sure to subscribe to the podcast feed
of your choice as well to stay up to
date with all of the latest happenings
on the AI Native Dev. Thanks for tuning
in. Bye.
Yes, and keep the comments coming. Thank
you.
Thanks for tuning in. Join us next time
on the AI Native Dev, brought to you by
Tesseract.